<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc version 1.6.27 (Ruby 3.1.4) -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-king-rokui-ainetops-usecases-00" category="info" submissionType="IETF" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.17.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ainetops">AI for Network Operations</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-king-rokui-ainetops-usecases-00"/>
    <author fullname="D. King">
      <organization>Lancaster University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>d.king@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="R. Rokui">
      <organization>Ciena</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rrokui@ciena.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <area>IRTF</area>
    <keyword>AI</keyword>
    <keyword>ML</keyword>
    <keyword>Artificial Intelligence</keyword>
    <keyword>Use Cases</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document explores the role of the IETF and IRTF in advancing Artificial Intelligence for Network Operations (AINetOps) in networking, 
         focusing on requirements for IETF protocols and architectures. AINetOps applies AI techniques to automate and optimize network operations, 
         enabling use cases such as reactive troubleshooting, proactive assurance, closed-loop optimization, misconfiguration detection, and 
         virtual operator assistance.</t> 
         
      <t>The document also addresses multi-layer aspects like IP/optical planning and optimization, aiming to guide 
         the evolution of protocols to support AINetOps-driven network management.</t>       
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>
        Status information for this document may be found at <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Discussion of this document has taken place during IETF Side Meetings.
      </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
        <eref target="https://github.com/danielkinguk/ai4net/aiops"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The increasing complexity of modern networks has driven the need for innovative approaches to 
         network operations and management. Artificial Intelligence for Network Operations (AINetOps) has emerged
         as a transformative concept, leveraging artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) 
         to automate, enhance, and optimize network management tasks. AINetOps offers the potential to 
         reduce operational costs, improve service reliability, and enhance user experiences by enabling 
         intelligent automation, predictive insights, and efficient decision-making.</t>
         
      <t>The IETF and IRTF play a critical role in defining the protocols, architectures, and standards 
         that underpin global networking. As AINetOps becomes integral to network operations, there is a 
         growing need to evaluate how existing IETF technologies can support AINetOps use cases and to 
         identify gaps that may require new or extended solutions. This document aims to outline key 
         AINetOps use cases, highlight associated technical challenges, and propose requirements for 
         protocols and architectures to address these challenges effectively.</t>   
         
      <t>The use cases considered in this document span multiple aspects of network operations, including
         reactive troubleshooting, proactive assurance (e.g., anomaly detection, predictive maintenance), 
         closed-loop optimization, and misconfiguration detection. Emerging capabilities, such as generative 
         AI for operational insights and virtual operator assistants, further emphasize the need for a 
         robust framework to support AI-driven network management. Additionally, the multi-layered nature 
         of these use cases, encompassing IP, optical, and cross-layer optimization, underscores the 
         complexity of integrating AINetOps into existing networks.</t>
         
      <t>This document provides a foundation for advancing IETF protocols and architectures to enable 
         AINetOps-driven network operations by exploring these use cases, the requirements and their implications.</t>   
    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
      <t>Specific terms used within this document are as follows:</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>AINetOps:</dt>
        <dd>Artificial Intelligence for IT Operations, encompassing the use of AI and ML techniques to automate and optimize network operations.</dd>
       </dl> 
      <dl>
        <dt>Closed-Loop Optimization:</dt>
        <dd>Automated feedback-driven processes for continuously improving network performance and reliability.</dd>
       </dl>        
      <dl>
        <dt>Multi-Layer Optimization:</dt>
        <dd>Addressing cross-layer dependencies and optimizing resources across different network layers, such as IP and optical layers.</dd>
       </dl>           
      <dl>
        <dt>Operator-Assistant:</dt>
        <dd>A virtual expert system leveraging AI to assist network operators in decision-making and troubleshooting tasks, often enhanced by the use of Large Language Models (LLMs).</dd>
       </dl>                 
      <dl>
        <dt>Proactive Assurance:</dt>
        <dd>Predictive capabilities in network management, including anomaly detection, forecasting potential issues, and preventive actions.</dd>
       </dl>                 
      <dl>
        <dt>Reactive Assurance:</dt>
        <dd>The process of identifying and resolving network issues in response to observed faults or failures.</dd>
       </dl>                 
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="applicability">
      <name>Applicability of AI on Network Operations</name>
      <t>Artificial Intelligence (AI) has the potential to revolutionize network operations by addressing the inherent complexity, scale, and dynamic nature of modern networks. 
         By applying AI techniques, network operators can transition from traditional manual or rule-based operations to intelligent, automated systems capable of real-time 
         adaptation, predictive insights, and optimized decision-making. This section outlines key areas where AI can be applied effectively in network operations, leveraging 
         both data-driven models and domain-specific knowledge.</t>

      <section anchor="anomaly">
      <!-- anchor is an optional attribute -->
        <name>Anomaly Detection and Predictive Analytics</name>
        <t>AI techniques, such as supervised and unsupervised learning, can detect anomalies in real-time by analyzing vast amounts of network telemetry data. Predictive models 
           enable the identification of potential network issues, such as link failures or traffic congestion, before they occur. Techniques like time-series forecasting and 
           clustering help in identifying patterns and trends that signal imminent failures or suboptimal behavior.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="closed-loop">
        <name>Closed-Loop Automation</name>
        <t>Closed-loop automation systems use AI to adjust network configurations based on real-time data dynamically. Reinforcement learning (RL) algorithms and policy-based 
           decision frameworks can automate traffic engineering, resource allocation, and fault remediation tasks. AI-driven systems ensure optimal network performance without 
           human intervention by continually monitoring network state and applying corrective actions.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="root-cause">
        <name>Root Cause Analysis</name>
        <t>AI accelerates the process of root cause analysis (RCA) by correlating events across the network and identifying the underlying cause of network issues. Techniques 
           such as graph-based analysis, natural language processing (NLP) for log analysis, and knowledge graph representations allow for faster and more accurate diagnosis, 
           reducing mean time to resolution (MTTR).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-management">
        <name>Policy and Configuration Management</name>
        <t>AI can assist in automating the generation, validation, and enforcement of network policies and configurations. For instance, generative AI models can create configuration 
           templates tailored to specific network requirements, including QoS settings, ACLs, or tunnel configurations. Furthermore, AI can validate configurations for compliance 
           with defined policies and detect misconfigurations that could lead to security vulnerabilities or operational inefficiencies.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="traffic-optimization">
        <name>Traffic Optimization</name>
        <t>Machine learning models can optimize traffic flow by dynamically adjusting routing protocols, load balancing, and bandwidth allocation. AI-powered traffic optimization 
           considers multiple factors such as latency, packet loss, and link utilization, enabling networks to adapt to changing conditions in real time.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="multi-layer">
        <name>Cross-Layer and Multi-Layer Optimization</name>
        <t>AI can address the dependencies between different network layers, such as IP and optical layers, by integrating data and decision-making across these layers. 
           Multi-layer optimization algorithms ensure resource efficiency and performance by aligning the goals of individual layers, such as minimizing power consumption at 
           the physical layer while maintaining SLA guarantees at the application layer.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="operator-assistant">
        <name>Operator Assistance</name>
        <t>AI-powered operator assistants function as virtual network engineers, providing real-time recommendations, insights, and automated solutions. These systems use NLP 
           for interface interaction, deep learning for anomaly classification, and contextual understanding to enhance operator decision-making.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cleanup">
        <name>Network Cleanup and Maintenance</name>
        <t>AI can automate cleanup operations by identifying and resolving transient issues, removing redundant configurations, and optimizing resource utilization. These tasks 
           may involve the identification of "stale" network states or unused resources, enabling networks to operate more efficiently.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="examples">
      <name>Use Cases</name>
      <t>This section explores specific use cases for applying Artificial Intelligence (AI) in network operations, focusing on their architectural, procedural, and protocol-level 
         requirements. Each use case highlights how AI can be leveraged to address challenges in network management and optimization, while identifying the relevant IETF 
         protocols, interfaces, and data models that are involved or need enhancement.</t>
         
      <t>For every use case described, the following dimensions are examined to provide a comprehensive understanding of its implications and requirements.</t>

      <t>Architecture: The high-level architecture necessary to support the use case, including control-plane and data-plane interactions, as well as integration points for AI-driven systems.</t>

      <t>Interfaces and APIs: The key interfaces between AI systems and network elements, including management APIs (e.g., NETCONF, RESTCONF, gNMI) and telemetry interfaces.</t>
 
      <t>Protocols: IETF protocols involved in enabling the use case, and potential extensions to existing protocols to accommodate AI-driven operations.</t>
 
      <t>Data Models: The data models required to represent network state, telemetry, policies, and configurations.</t>
 
      <t>Processes and Procedures: Workflow considerations for integrating AI systems into existing operational practices, including training, validation, and deployment.</t>
 
      <t>Alignment with IETF Standards: Analysis of how existing IETF standards can be leveraged or extended to support the use case.</t>
 
    </section>

	
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This work has benefited from several discussions at the IETF and the AI4NETWORK Side Meetings.</t> 

    </section>

   <section anchor="contributors" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

      <t>The following authors contributed to this document:</t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt="">
          <![CDATA[
   TBA
   Lancaster University
   United Kingdom
   Email: TBA      
          ]]>
       </artwork>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
  <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
      </references>
      <references title="Informative References">
    </references>
    </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
